A Guide to the Papers of Virginius Dabney, 1941-1980
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney 1941-1980
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-af
This collection consists of ca. 630 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 12 October 1982.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
This addition to the Virginius Dabney Papers consists of ca. 630 items, 1941-1980, including correspondence, financial statements, typescript (copy), and near-print and printed material concerning awards received, the bicentennial celebration, civic projects, Dabney's retirement, and various publications. Linwood Holton and Mills Godwin, governors of Virginia, are correspondents.
Contents List
- Anne Frank House 1971, 15 items. (Box 1)
- Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities 1969-1980, 31 items. (Box 1)
- Awards 1971-1978, 48 items. (Box 1)
- The Bank of Virginia 1968-1973, 37 items. (Box 1)
- The Bank of Virginia 1968-1972, 36 items. (Box 1)
  - Thomas C. Boushall
  - Frederick Deane, Jr.
  - William T. Gordon
  - Herbert C. Moseley
- Bodine and Associates 1962 (1969-1971) 1975, 26 items. (Box 1)
- Brandt and Brandt 1941-1953, 1967-1978, 144 items. (Box 1)
- The Central National Bank with TMs, "The American Revolution and Its Meaning for Today" 1975-1976, 31 items. (Box 1)
- Green Springs 1969-1974, 26 items. (Box 2)
- John Marshall Hotel Project 1976-1977, 34 items. (Box 2)
- Libraries: Governor's Conference on Library Service 1970-1971, 27 items. (Box 2)
- The Markle Foundation 1969, 11 items. (Box 2)
- National Endowment for the Humanities 1969-1975, 46 items. (Box 2)
- Population Control 1969, 2 items. (Box 2)
- Retirement of Virginius Dabney 1968-1969, 71 items. (Box 2)
- Richmond Independence Bicentennial Commission 1973-1979, n.d., 40 items. (Box 2)
- Virginius Dabney as the subject of a dissertation 1972, 1977, 5 items. (Box 2)